One, two...
Are you from Lviv? Yes.
We`re brothers, and here brother said...
Vasya, this Malevich isn`t cool,
and this fool says that he is good.
When Tkachenko left, I led at TSN for a couple of months.
Oh my God, we don't have a prime minister.
On the 5th day she said, couldn't you kick him?
Slap him in the face.
On the 10th day, well, not so much, just a little,
why are you slapping him in the face like that?
As long as you don't have 100,000 on the
Maidan, we won't do anything.
Everyone was on time.
Even Yanukovych was on time.
In Ukraine, if you gave money, you are a good boy.
Again, such an age, such a disease, this age.
Let's do it like in Moscow,
everything is fine there.
He came and said, like this, you will act as I say,
and that's it.
I would say that this Zelenskyy and
Zaluzhnyi is a very simple story.
Someone doesn't want Putin to die...
Lady of Lviv, Yaffarion.
Here is such a subtle moment.
What do you want?
Hey, you assholes!
Why the hell are you talking in Russian?
Yermak is terrible.
I will shoot myself in front of your eyes
for the sake of the victory of Ukraine.
What is this content?
Let me smear the f**king spirituality.
Only I will personally give you
a gun so that you kill them.
Mykola Veresen, the meter of Ukrainian
television and Ukrainian journalism.
Today we have a conversation from the
appropriate to the taboo.
And, by the way, not a meter,
but a meter and seventy-eight.
I would like to clarify this.
Watch on the YouTube channel of Natalia Moseichuk, Mykola Veresen.
Moseychuk + He`s called Mykola Veresen.
You sat? Hi.
This means the beginning,
we usually do this.
I know, I have some experience in TV.
Not a big one, but... A little.
Especially with this director.
Clear.
And with the director, yes.
Not much has changed.
Well, it has changed and it has not changed.
You can't say so clearly.
All these are conditions.
Both phrases are correct.
People do not change and people change.
Both of these phrases are correct.
They do not change and they change.
Television does not change and it changes.
Ukraine does not change and it changes.
Here... It will not change... You
can't say so accurately and determine.
Only your phrase does not change.
How do you start the broadcast?
I`m called Mykola Veresen.
Yes, yes.
That's the name.
It's true.
Thank you that we were able
to get you out of Lviv.
Yes, this is God.
This is not me.
This is no one.
This is some kind of divine idea.
Because I really had to come to Kyiv.
I had things to do here.
And they called me here.
And I thought, well, if I'm already here, then why won't I come?
I never refuse.
Because I don't like it when
they refuse me.
Because I have such a profession as you do.
And it's obvious that when you consider something,
and then a person runs away at
the last moment, it's very unpleasant.
And I know what it's like so I never refuse.
Thank you.
Because, well, what?
If I had been in your place
and invited you, and you hadn't come at the last moment,
what would I have done?
I understand it.
I had such an attitude yesterday
when one person refused me.
And I was a little disappointed.
But I also want to say thank you to Den Borysovich Yanevsky.
Because he, sitting here in your place a
week ago, remembered how you, in 1991,
having, it seems, 20 dollars in your
pocket, paid for a car and went to Belarus.
And, in fact, today it is also the subject of our study with you.
Because you are a person who saw the
independence for 33 years and a little earlier.
And you have something to tell.
And I am interested in this, because all these
memories of people who sit in this chair,
they are very subjective,
but they are very fragmentary.
And the story consists of these fragments.
Because the views on it can be different.
But this is a testimony.
And I listened to you when you
said that people think in every way,
but you call for tolerance,
not Facebook emotions.
I am the same with my viewers.
I say, try to understand a person who has
seen these circumstances in this way.
And, probably, from 1991
and we will start... From 1989.
Do we have to start from 1989?
Well, yes.
At the BBC, I even remember, on August 16, 1989,
my voice sounded there for the first time.
That is, you are an inoagent speaking today's language.
I'm worse.
I didn't think about it.
In Russian, there is such a saying,
eyes are afraid, hands are doing.
I had the same thing.
And I was already somewhere at the end
of the 90s, at the beginning of the 00s,
I looked into the Penal Code of the Ukrainian SSR.
There was no Penal Code of the USSR.
What could be with me, right?
Each republic had its own Penal Code.
I found, there is an article about the betrayal
of the homeland in the form of espionage.
The main basis of it, it is to get a gain.
And since I worked at the BBC and received a gain,
I betrayed my homeland in the form of espionage.
15 years or shooting.
Cool.
So... Mr. Mykola, you
found a job for yourself.
I just didn't know.
Maybe if I had read it then, if
someone had suggested the Penal Code,
I might have said, no, no, no,
let's not do it.
And what did the work at the BBC look like? Tell me.
Well, how?
In 1989.
In 1989 it was...
Well, it was a disaster.
Because you didn't even... Well, first
of all, I'll tell you subjectively.
My first half of the year, I
don't have much time, once a month,
two times a month, maybe three times a month
my temperature jumped to
40 degrees for one hour.
After an hour, it dropped again to 36.6.
And then I kept living.
And then there was the report again.
And then it was... Well, it wasn't
now, I pressed, you called, and that's it.
And then I had to order.
So, tell me, there was no office, right?
Well, I don't remember.
People think it's an office.
073 or 079.
You call 073 or 079.
I still remember.
And you say, the girl is from Smolny, but
not from Smolny, the girl is from London.
Obviously, a major is sitting next to the girl.
And he is recording all the people who are calling in London.
And when one calls the BBC,
it's obvious that he is not only signaling.
Well, I was then shown by the mayor of Odesa, Gurvits.
He laughed a lot.
We met in the Verkhovna Rada.
He showed me... So, there
was already independence,
but top officials received on
the table the interception of the radio voices.
And he showed me, like, the enemy of the people.
Here is Veresen, here is such
a... And there was also the word 'secrecy.'
What did you say in London?
Everything that could be listened to.
It was very funny, because you could listen,
and the next morning you could look at yourself at the table.
The same thing as yesterday.
Yesterday, as a normal citizen, you could
catch the BBC frequency if it wasn't muted.
And listen to it.
And Shcherbitsky got it on the table in the morning.
Printed one.
And why did the choice fall on you?
Nobody wanted to work.
Well, who wants to go to prison?
Who wants to go to Siberia?
Nobody wants to.
It's just Veresen, idiot.
That's why I got there myself.
And that's why somehow they... Well,
there are no such people there anymore.
Those were old times.
It was such a classic BBC, Russian service.
Well, there were no others then.
Then the Ukrainian one appeared.
And when Techer came here, Chornovyl
asked her why there was no Ukrainian.
And she said, well, we can't.
How many languages do we have
on the territory of the Soviet Union?
Only 15 languages of the republic.
There is also autonomy.
She says we don't have such a budget.
We can't speak every language.
Well, that's a lot of money.
It all costs a lot of money.
And so there was a Russian
service, a classic one.
And they treated me very well
because I think they didn't understand
why the hell I needed it.
A spy in Ukraine.
Yes, yes, yes.
Well, I was lucky today because
Veresen came in February.
And why did Veresen appear, in principle?
Oh, it's so delusional... It's so... As I tell you
now, it's not far from here, by the way.
It's quite close to the madhouse.
A car will come after me from the madhouse.
So, I wasn't a dissident.
But I worked at the BBC.
And among the dissidents, they
investigated me for a very long time.
Well, those who were already...
Well, you were even the opposite.
You were from an elite club.
No, my father was a member of
the Central Committee.
He was the head of the Verkhovna Rada at the time.
Well, this is such a nominal position.
Now the head of the Verkhovna Rada is something.
And then it was just...
Well, gilded youth.
One way or another.
Gilded youth.
Well, among gilded youth, there
was gold, there was diamond,
and there was bad.
Really?
Because it didn't always correspond...
Your behavior didn't always correspond...
For example, if you study international relations,
international law, international
relations, then this is gold, really.
Petro Oleksievich is gold.
Yes.
And there, well, all
these people... And you?
All these people, they... They went to
restaurants, they lived so luxuriously.
We didn't go to restaurants because I didn't have any money.
And so it is believed that those who were there,
we also looked at them, they were all like that.
They dressed up... Like people.
Yes, and so on.
I entered the Faculty of History because they had refused me.
I wanted to study international relations, but
academician Shlipakov, Arnold Nikolayevich,
the main internationalist of Ukraine,
director of the Institute of
International Relations and World Economics,
he was there, now he is gone.
My father called him, we met, and
he said, listen, this is not a profession.
International... This is
something international.
Go to the history department.
And I went to the history department.
And so I, in August... Well, I can
tell you, this is an interesting story.
I am very responsible, despite the fact
that I do not look like a responsible person,
I have never looked like that.
But I always thought, well, how do I need
to... If I promised, what should I do?
And I married.
And I had no money.
Well, I worked as a lecturer, for 105 rubles.
My wife got 110 rubles, by the way.
Remembered.
My father did not give me money.
Well, he almost did not give me money.
We had such a Calvinist family.
Such a Protestantism.
And so I was looking for a job.
I was preparing students for universities, and so on.
And I wanted...
Not that I wanted...
I thought so.
And someone told me, there is an
opportunity to work on the Ukrainian radio.
I have already forgotten which one.
On the international or on the Ukrainian.
And you did not have a division?
So that you would be teachers of history, no?
There was no such thing?
No. So I was a lecturer.
Oh, you were.
I worked for 105 rubles. I was a lecturer.
Well, that's not enough.
And besides that, I wanted something else.
School or university or institute?
No.
It was a pedagogy school.
And I was thinking, how could I work
somewhere else for 30 rubles, for 10, for 20.
And here I had corruption.
Here I had a case of corruption.
I started walking around important
people on the radio.
And one of the important
people told me that
his daughter does not
know whether she will enter
a pedagogical school.
And it was so very popular there.
The number of people in one place was some kind of terrible.
He says, if you help my daughter to
enter, then I will take you here.
Since I am a bad corruptionist, I went to
the headmaster and told him all this.
There is such a situation.
Then the headmaster came to me.
And told me not to panic, that the
girl knows school subjects well.
That is, no bribing was needed.
And I came to that boy and said, here it is, I did something.
And, of course, as always, the
Soviet Union has never changed,
and the modern Ukraine is also such that it
is possible to promise, but not to fulfill.
So no?
And I go out in such a gloom from
Khreshchatyk 26, and there is such a girl Katya.
It was just such a strange time when
Gorbachev let for the first
time foreigners
into the territory of the Soviet Union.
Previously, if you did not have a goal,
a student, a tourist, a relative,
that is, just Vasya Pupkin ...
This is now the United States of America, roughly speaking.
No, no, anyone can be there, depending on
whether they will give you a visa or not.
And here you just couldn't say,
I'm going to the Soviet Union.
What will you do there?
And I'll just come, settle in a hotel, I'll live there, and go to exhibitions.
Well, this Katya is walking around,
and I'm going in a gloomy mood,
and she says to me, why are you gloomy?
This is the first foreign English woman,
who was probably the
first in Kyiv, who just came,
rented an apartment, and started to live.
Well, as if now you could go to
Warsaw or London if you have a visa.
And I say, well, yes, and I tell her the whole story.
She says, listen, I used to work at
... At the BBC, the Russian service.
I looked at her as if she was mad, just like that.
Well, because the BBC is like God here,
and there is a little higher
than God, and there is the BBC.
Well, the BBC is under the carpet, roughly speaking.
Have you ever listened to the BBC?
Yes, but this is also quality.
Well, there are no such analogs now.
And I just missed the buzz.
Well, something went off, so as to support me, I guess.
And so ... Half a year
or more has passed.
I was at my father's house.
My father had not been a deputy, but
he was a member of the Central Committee.
And then my wife calls me with a groaning voice.
And she says that Katya called.
I say, well, okay.
You don't understand, she didn't call from Kyiv.
She called from London.
She called from the BBC.
And I didn't know anything.
She didn't say that she was from the BBC.
She only said later.
And I gave your phone, so wait.
Now, from London itself, from the BBC,
you will be called to your father's apartment.
And indeed, they called.
And so I took the phone and said, give me a
couple of hours, because I'm not at home.
I told my father.
My father says, well, just work, don't lie.
Since the BBC, after all, not everyone has a good attitude to it.
And I, yes, for the first time, about Chornobyl.
I was from Chornobyl.
By the way, in Chornobyl, indeed, with my father.
Well, in those times, when there was still the red forest, all these.
Well, I told him what I saw there.
And then, then there was such, in foreign radio stations.
They understood that they were
in Munchin, London, or in Washington.
And I'm here, so they didn't
want to ask the questions
that could put me in jail.
They suddenly, and don't ask why either.
Eyes are afraid, hands are doing.
At the end as always they asked,
maybe you wanted to say something
about what we didn't ask you.
Well, because I took the initiative myself.
So that I said, seeing what the circumstances are around me.
KGB, not KGB.
And I suddenly, I don't know why.
Maybe for the same reason, I'm here.
This is how the stars aligned.
I say, you see, this is not a Chornobyl disaster.
This is a disaster of that system that came in 1917.
What the hell did I say that?
Did you say something like that with your mouth?
I explained why it all happened.
These are all consequences of previous events.
Well, in short, then the body temperature rose to 40 degrees.
Then, my wife, as I remember now,
put on my head some rag with vinegar.
I started thinking about how to fool the KGB.
I decided that in September I will be Veresen.
And in October I will be Zhovten.
And in November I will be Lystopad.
And in December, regardless of what, I will be Hruden.
And the KGB, of course, will never find me.
Well, of course, such seasonality, such cunningness, how would they?
And on September 3, indeed, I wrote some text, read it.
It's 079, the girl, London, etc., etc., etc.
Then you wait, and you don't know
when they will call you.
Until three o'clock.
And you couldn't go out.
You had to stand or sit next to the
phone and wait until it all happened.
Then one report, the second, the third, the fourth.
I thought, well, why would change
the name to Zhovten?
And I stayed as Veresen.
Veresen.
So there is nothing extraordinary.
I don't have a birthday in September.
There is nothing in common.
It just happened like that.
Well, look, meters are not born, I think so.
Meters are made, and this
is such a hard work.
You have to break this wall.
If you were from an elite family, or you were
from a farm family or a labor family.
It's such a thing.
You have to go and work.
And here is 1991.
When I asked Den Borisovich, I said, where were you in 1991?
You know, people still can't realize
that there were a few journalists then.
Yes, yes, yes.
People think that it's like now, you know,
20 TV channels and about 5 thousand journalists.
A million, yes.
Yes, in the country.
Not in the country, but in Kyiv.
And people need to be explained.
Because you were chosen, and you remain chosen.
You are meters.
You are Ukrainian meters.
This is a question of what we should be proud of.
That we don't have a portrait of Ukraine and so on.
We have it all.
The only thing is that we don't show it very willingly.
And we don't praise our own.
And we never show it.
And we don't really like to talk about it.
Well, this is, as for me, the Ukrainian feature.
I listened to you, you also complained about it.
And very correct.
Not like me now.
Demonstratively.
And that's why I want to learn about 1991.
How it all started.
Because Den Borysovych
shouted out here, he said,
we have no state, I'll tell
you how the elections happened.
I'll tell you that he said such a trigger thing.
And there were even reactions to what he said.
I got messages from other people
who were participants of those historical days.
In the elections,
in the parliament, and then in the trip to Belarus, and so on.
And people are a little bit offended
because they think that Den Borysovych
exceeded the level of epitome.
And I always say that everyone
has their own point of view here,
and we are assembling such a historical puzzle,
from different people, and now we will
assemble it for you to understand
who and how watched those events.
Who were you in 1991? You are
a correspondent, a BBC journalist, after all.
Yes.
You no longer work in a pedagogical school?
I left the pedagogical school in 1990.
You are a journalist.
I went there in 1990, and I went to
London in 1990,
thinking whether I should stay
or return.
I had a whole revolution in my head.
And for two months I was choosing.
I came back, and then the students just laid on the Maidan.
And I remember that there was a beautiful story.
I was still working in the pedagogical school.
And there was supposed to be a meeting in the Ukrainian House.
I don't know what it's called now. It's the Ukrainian House, isn't it?
Well, yes.
I'm sorry, then it was a museum of Lenin.
There was no Ukrainian House at that time.
There was no such phrase.
For such a phrase – Sybir.
The one they call the European Square.
The European Square.
The students of pedagogical
school and some veterans gathered there.
I don't remember what occasion it was.
And on the Maidan, it's already there...
Today he posted a photo with Plyushch and Kravchuk back then.
Yes, I remember it all.
When he was performing at the Tribune of the Verkhovna Rada.
They came, there was a hall in
Lenin's museum,
and there was a party leading something.
And they gave me a word.
It was their mistake.
And I went out to say something there.
Then I say, the only thing I didn't understand is why you are sitting here.
All say, what?
Well, Maidan is 200 meters away and there are students.
Why aren't you there, where the students are?
And they looked at me like that.
Well, those veterans of the Brownian
movement, they were somehow surprised.
There was such a magazine 'Ukraine.'
There was such a huge tab.
There was Maidan, the students, and it was written in large letters
'The First Pedagogical School is with you.'
So I'm a revolutionary, I would say.
Lenin, damn it, Vladimir Ilyich.
And you went to Belarus as who?
No, it was already later.
It was already after the real independence.
Because there is such a Vladimir Filenko,
and there are a few more of my old friends.
And we all together believe that the independence day is on December the 1st.
Because on 24th, 360 people said that we were independent.
And then 91% of Ukrainians said that we were independent.
And we didn't really believe that.
Because exactly half a
year before that, in March,
72% said that we were for the
preservation of the Soviet Union.
Renewed.
So there was ... No, well, something happened
to the people that they responded later.
Well, half a year is not... It doesn't matter.
And there were such prices.
There were such prices.
You say 20$ to Minsk.
So, from Donetsk to Kyiv in August costed 10$.
So why did you go there?
Then there was no Internet.
And everything was at the level of rumors.
And something happens in ... So, the
Ukrainians voted for the independence.
Complete shock.
Complete.
Moscow is just ...
And we are brothers.
And here the brothers said ...
And then the conversation begins that there is something there.
Someone is flying to Minsk.
There is something there.
And Yeltsin is in Minsk.
Shushkevich is there.
And Kravchuk.
And that's all.
And there was some kind of ...
Well, then there were always drinking sprees.
From the second of December, when
they began to recognize the referendum,
the Poles, the Hungarians, which is strange now, and the Canadians.
This is what I remember.
I had a consul, a friend, Nestor Hayovsky.
And he was just
... We were sitting.
And the future wife of Yushchenko organized one
of the big events in Lybid, in the restaurant.
There were meetings of deputies and journalists.
There were five of them.
Four.
And he was so ... I remember everyone
saying, Hayovsky is going, Hayovsky is going.
And we went out like that.
And he walked by like that.
As there is recognition.
And this was such a series of these events, to put it mildly.
And there was another one somewhere in the hotel Kyiv.
And they began to dig into it.
Well, there were foreigners.
There was a lot of knowledge
through the Moscow Bureau,
through London, through
Washington, through Brussels.
And they say, listen, something is happening there.
And we are like, what?
And what?
And how is it going there?
The planes have already started to fly rarely.
The trains don't work.
Well, that's it.
The Soviet Union is over.
Here.
And night.
Night.
And the Guardian comes.
Martha is with the Guardian.
Said that she ordered a taxi there.
I say, well, what?
Well, so let's go.
You are going?
I say, well, I'm going.
Then I understood why Belarus is the way it is today.
Why?
Because there was a reconstruction in Moscow,
movement, as it is called in young slang.
In Ukraine, there were points of it. We saw it there too.
They didn't care about the currency anymore,
it was possible to exchange it on the street.
In short, there were some obvious changes.
People's Movement, Chornovyl, a lot of
dissidents were released, they came back.
In short, something is happening.
We came to Minsk, and they didn't even
understand what they were talking about.
They had the same salaries, I remember there was such a shock.
All the journalists gathered, there were 7 of us.
Time, Guardian, Christian Science Monitor,
something else, but I won't go into details.
We were in some kind of cafe, there
were a few of them in Kyiv and they were called
cooperative restaurants, they started to appear.
And since the exchange rate was
crazy, something for a dollar,
and we didn't have money, as we hold them now,
carefully folded, because they were pennies.
If you earned, let's say, 500,
it was considered that you were a billionaire
if you had a salary of 200 dollars a month.
200 dollars in Kyiv in 1990, in 1991,
well, that's it, life was successful.
And that's why it was so intense.
And here someone runs and says, Yeltsin came,
we need a taxi, we need to go to the airport.
And we all jump, hands in
our pockets and on the table like this.
We threw it away because
it's 20 cents, 50 cents,
30, 50 cents, well, something like that.
I was the last one to throw money.
Such a small pile of these squashed
rubles, and an oppressive silence fell.
The whole hall of this dining room, because
it's not a restaurant, it's a dining room,
the waiters ran out, all of them.
Because for them, still, 200 rubles salary is good.
And we threw away, probably, a thousand rubles.
And a thousand rubles was there, 3 dollars, for 7 people.
And we threw it away and ran
away, it's not money, it's not money.
Then I flew to Georgia for the war.
I just had a translator on the table, and there was a driver.
And I put a thousand rubles on the table,
I say, to eat, to order something.
And they also looked at me, wow, a thousand rubles.
And it's nothing, it's 5 dollars or 4 dollars.
Well, and we came, yes,
really talked, we saw
Shushkevych, we saw Yeltsin, I think I even asked some of them.
How close were you to them?
Well, then there was no ban.
Then to stand next to Yeltsin is, well,
as we sit with you.
Well, the only thing is that there was
protection, but it was much easier then.
On the airfield, in Kyiv, everywhere we met near the stairs.
It was normal.
Then already during Kuchma's time,
it began to change a little.
During Kravchuk's tie, you just came,
oh, you're a journalist? Okay.
Was it a ritual thing, they had
already signed an agreement?
No, then we figured out everything as it was.
Nobody, just one person of us all, got
there in Viskuli, or where they signed it.
The beginning was like this. Yeltsin brought
a document, laid it on the table, and said,
'Leonid Makarovich, you can do whatever
you want, mark it, change it, mark it,
write it down, do whatever you
want, but you have to accept it.'
Kravchuk said, 'You know, a
week ago, I was elected president
with the pre-election program
for the independence of Ukraine.
It was somehow strange that was now for the Union.
A week ago, I was against
the Union, and now…'
And then this phrase came up in the sauna.
In the sauna, not because
they were naked there,
it's not the top officials,
but the country's second persons.
It was just that it was free.
They just came in in suits, there was just a room.
And there, this geopolitical
reality of the previously named
Union of Soviet Socialist
Republics ceases to exist.
It's just that they thought for two hours,
and the phrase 'geopolitical reality of the
previously named Union of Soviet
Socialist Republics ceases to exist.'
And then it got easier.
Yes.
But it all started only when Kravchuk said,
'No, no, no, guys, we're
not joking here, it's serious.'
Integral nationalists spoke
out against it here in Kyiv,
like Stepan Ilkovich Khmara,
and Chornovyl... there was a lot of diversity there.
Why, Mykola, didn't we make such a quantum
jump with little blood as Baltica did?
It's impossible.
Why?
It`s all just conversations that...
Because the Baltic States...
Well, you will be guilty, not me...
We are not Europeans.
The Baltics considered themselves
from the very beginning to be Europeans,
we became Europeans only in 2014.
But now we paved the path somehow.
Estonians...
I was in Estonia in 1976 with my father.
I was walking around Tallinn.
There was a home cathedral in every capital.
And I came up to go on and they said,
''Excuse me, please, we are already
closed. Do you want something?''
I said, ''Yes, I would like to... Where are you from?''
I said, ''I'm from Kyiv.''
''What language do you speak there?''
I said, ''Ukrainian.''
''Please, come in.''
Forest brothers.
That's the question.
I lied because in
Kyiv Ukrainian is... Yes.
Yes, of course.
It was used by 0.5%. But I understood
because I was already trained in nationalism.
Did your father speak Ukrainian or
Russian at the Academy of Sciences?
It's also a complicated story.
While there was Shelest, everyone spoke Ukrainian.
The plenum of the Central Committee was held in Ukrainian.
Really?
Yes.
Until 1972, the plenums of the Central
Committee during Shelest were in Ukrainian.
Then Shcherbitsky came and gradually,
then Malanchuk, this famous Lviv guy.
I had a fight with him twice, by the way.
With the main enemy of all of Ukraine.
It's very strange that he is from Halychyna.
He is from Galichina, yes.
And that's why they always didn't want to be Soviet.
And here, apart from Galichina, Volhynia,
Bukovina... Was there any strategy?
Well, look, if in the
Baltic states, for example,
this umbilical cord was not
cut by the so-called Soviets,
and they remembered it, and it was important
for them as a language, and so on...
Forty years ago, not all of them died, not all of them.
Well, yes.
And in our country, especially in Halychyna, at least the Bandera movement,
what about in Kyiv, Kharkiv, and Odesa?
I understand that they had more dissidents in the Baltic states.
They didn't have dissidents.
It's a very complicated issue.
The statistics there seem to be Ukrainian and Baltic.
The question is that the
Baltics themselves once told me
that they all are nationalists.
We don't have any non-nationalists.
Unlike the Ukrainians, not all of them are nationalists in Ukraine.
But if they are already nationalists, they're
so passionate that we still need to learn from them,
Because they are all a little bit.
And a little bit like this.
And what language do you speak?
And if Ukraine becomes a nationalist,
then we will burn
the commandments of the Party.
That's why it was like that.
In 1991, the communists voted for the
creation of another state, of course, Ukraine.
And what is the concept?
How do they see this state?
What did they want?
They didn't see anything.
They had to hide.
This is the same conversation.
Look, 33 years.
We are standing next to that post.
And we are talking again.
We will keep talking until the generation changes.
When Yosep Zisels teaches us,
when I talk to him, I say,
Yosep, you are a smart person.
You know everything.
You were in prison for nationalism with such a nickname.
And he says, well, it's the same as we have.
He says, I mean, when they say 40 years, they were walking in the desert.
So we are the same.
I say, what do you
mean, he says, well, look,
in the 90s, 10 years, the
communists were in power.
The 00s - Komsomol people.
The 10s - pioneers.
We have to survive the Octobrists.
And now you are 40 years old.
So now we still have 5 years, 4 years,
6 years, and we will almost lose them.
Here.
What did they want from the country?
They were running away.
I was one of the few, even among journalists.
I went down to the cinema hall
of the Verkhovna Rada on August 24th,
where the communists were going to decide
how to vote for them on Independence Day.
And I realized that the concept is this.
There is a quiet life here, more or less.
Kravchuk, the second secretary of the Central Committee, is a head.
And what Yeltsin will do there, we don't know.
And we are afraid of him because he is such an anti-communist.
And let's separate and protect ourselves.
In Moscow, they will ban the Communist
Party and maybe they will all be put in prison.
Nobody knew then.
Whether they will ban or not, imprison or not.
And we are here, an autonomous
Ukrainian republic, with our own legislation.
The majority of the Verkhovna Rada
are Communists, 239,
with the Socialists together.
And we will live as we lived before.
We will not build communism,
maybe not even socialism, but at
least we will not build nationalism.
So wait, if Poland was a social camp,
then the leaders would come out and
open the archives, at least, of the KGB.
Listen, what are we talking about?
In 1991, after the independence,
when it was announced that there
would be a vote on December 1st,
presidential candidates began to emerge, including Chornovil.
I came to him literally across the road,
he lived in a hotel Kyiv, and I will not lie,
he did not say that he would win the election and become president.
But everyone around him said that he would become president.
And already in 1997, literally
a year before his death,
we met, we had good
relations with Vyacheslav Maksimovich.
And he says, Mykola, it's good that I didn't become president.
I say, why?
He says, well, I think that only now
the civil war would have ended.
90% of the population of Ukraine
didn't have nationalism.
The Ukrainian language?
What are we talking about?
I always joke that in Khreshchatyk five
people spoke the Ukrainian language.
Four of them were from the diaspora,
and I was speaking in surzhik.
He did not evoke such strong feelings as
Yanukovych did for us, the Orange Party.
Well, wait, this is not the issue.
No, why does he talk about the civil war?
Because ... Did he really think
that people would rise against him?
Well, it wasn't like that ... Not
against him, against the ideas.
Well, against the ideas.
People for 70 years had been told that the Soviet Union was good.
And here comes a person who says, no, the Soviet Union is bulls**t.
What do you think?
There is such a magic button, where you press
it and everyone will change their mind.
Very few people thought so.
It was gradual.
Volyn and Bukovina were still communists.
A quasi-European view,
if we take the vote in the Verkhovna Rada,
had Kyiv, which was surprising, because
Kyiv was entirely Russian-speaking,
but everyone understood that ...
The capital.
And Galichina.
And in Volyn, the communists also came in.
In short, it's all just talk
that it can be skipped somehow.
There will be no quick changes.
It is necessary for the country to grow.
When we were sitting with
Zhvanecki, he said to me,
Mykola, the country must come up.
It just won't jump.
It is necessary for it to prepare.
And it's true.
And I have long said that I am a
supporter of natural historical processes.
When they say now, it was necessary earlier, it was necessary ...
You won't say to a woman, why
didn't you give birth in two months?
Why did you wait for nine months?
No one says that.
So does the nation.
The Belarusians only come to their senses in 2020.
Something started to come
out on the streets.
The Russians haven't come to their senses yet.
The Georgians have come to their senses yet.
The Azerbaijanis haven't come to their senses yet.
TV.
When you have already come there,
I want you to tell as a person who
watched the world from his place,
from the place of a TV presenter, a journalist.
A person who came to a temple of art.
What can I say?
Contemporary, but art.
Well, you are immediately on the channel 1+1.
No, I started to work...
I didn't like television at all.
Because in BBC I did everything myself.
From the beginning to the end.
I was not dependent on anyone.
I ran, took interviews, then cut this film.
Then they cut the film.
Wrote.
In short, it was all mine and I knew how I worked.
Here is the cameraman.
He sets up.
Here is the sound.
There is the light.
And you are always around with
a lot of people.
You depend on them all.
I was angry.
But I was convinced by Sashko Krivenko.
And the first thing that started.
Not Rodnyansky?
No, no, no.
This is before Rodnyansky.
At first, Sasha Tkachenko had afterword.
Yes.
Parallel.
I don't remember which of them.
The first or the second.
Mykola Kniazhynsky created MNC Internews.
There was.
And I, since I earned money.
And then there was such a system
of traveling abroad.
That you had to pay.
That is, you can be taken by the
Minister of Foreign Affairs on a plane.
But it doesn't mean that you will
live there for free.
And since few people had currency,
I was sometimes taken by ministers.
Or the president Kuchma once took me.
And I flew with them.
And since I flew there, I just
had money so that I could live there in a hotel.
Eat and so on.
Tkachenko says, 'You're going to fly anyway.'
Well, yes.
You will still work for the BBC. Yes.
So I'll give you a cameraman.
So you shoot something there and that's it.
So I started shooting.
And the same with Kniazhynsky.
I worked with him.
I had Windows to the World.
This is the first non-governmental
program in Ukraine called Windows to the World.
Then it turned out that Windows, then STB, and so on.
But firstly it was Windows to the World.
And we did it.
Rostik Hotin, Vitalik Portnikov and I.
We took turns for weeks.
A week for him, a week for me...
And then Yulia Mostova called me and
said, listen, one person is calling you now.
I say, what will he want from me?
She says he will want you to do
something on TV.
I resisted.
I didn't like this idea right away.
And then Lyosha called.
We met, went to the restaurant.
I can even remember what restaurant we went to if I wanted to.
And then he came up with this 1+1.
And there was a long fight there.
Lyosha, this is Oleksandr Rodnyansky for the viewers.
Yes.
Oleksandr Rodnyansky.
This is Yuhymovich.
He just then says, listen, look at Inter, it's
all in Russian, they have the highest ratings.
That is, the society didn't want it.
The journalists' language was Russian,
the business language was Russian,
the medical language was Russian.
How was it chosen in what language
the channel broadcasts?
It was very long.
There were discussions.
It was very, very...
Well, it wasn`t chosen.
By trial and error.
Then there was a long discussion, because
there was no peoplemeter, so
we couldn't calculate.
I remember that we called KVN.
KVN means an asphalt roller.
I mean, everything in
Russian was much better,
and there were one, two, three programs
among Russian ones, that's an asphalt roller.
You can turn off the signal and
not broadcast at all.
I don't know.
In the province where I lived,
for example, in Zhytomyr,
it didn't look like that, because
when the 1+1 began to broadcast,
the evening slot, everyone
was sitting next to the screen.
No, it was when he began to broadcast fully
when we had already done it.
When I was doing Taboo on 1+1...
And this convinced Aleksandr Yukhymovych.
Because he says, well, maybe
Russian, after all...
Inter, you see, it is like this, and it has a Russian language.
And we had to put in a lot more effort than Inter.
Inter is just so beautiful, and everyone is watching.
And 1+1... Did 1+1 rely on
intellectual viewers, on Ukrainian viewers?
We had an ideology. We always had an ideology.
In general, I still think that without an ideology it is difficult.
Pro-Ukrainian, pro-European, civilizational.
We came up with it there.
We discussed something, translated.
Lyosha, Oseledchik.
There were a lot of people who
came up with all these concepts.
But you consciously chose a
smaller segment of viewers, right?
I will be honest, I was undoubtedly
the deputy general producer.
But I concentrated more on my work.
And at my job, I said, I would not speak Russian.
I don't want to.
And what about politics at that time?
Such a channel is starting to get popular.
Politics... Very
few politicians.
Easy.
They all switched to Ukrainian.
Well, all nationalists.
Well, as it were.
Active ones.
How did they treat 1+1?
Oh, I don't know.
I had to... Who did
Rodnyansky come to?
He says I will have a Ukrainian-speaking channel.
1+1.
Well, at first he came to Lauder.
At first, it was
still... Investor.
Yes.
This is the son of Estee Lauder,
who made perfumes.
Yes.
It means that.
And American billionaires, they had such
a fashion that you need to make people happy.
If you have a lot of money,
and at Lauder, I think,
Ronald received something
like 9 billion or 7 billion.
That is, for him, this is such a missionary work.
Yes.
And he needed...
Someone gave him the
idea that in the east of Europe,
there are such new countries,
where they can watch TV.
Yes.
And he started looking.
And Lyosha was in Germany at that time, and he went there.
Somehow, I don't know how they found each other there.
And, in short, now it looks ridiculous.
I think... I can make a mistake.
This is purely speculation.
I think it's 22 million dollars.
Now you can't make half a channel
for that money.
And then you could make a full-fledged channel.
So, about asphalt roller.
And I remember one of the first of these peoplemeters came.
Calculated.
Taboo had...
Well, now there aren`t
such ratings as there were,
but now I would be appointed the leader
of all the channels in Ukraine at once.
Just all.
I had something like 52... Would
you be the head of the TV marathon?
No, not the head.
And the master, Maslyakov, and this is
such a nickname of Maslyakov, was the master.
He had something 42.
I came and said...
That is, the question is not in the language,
but in the quality of the product.
If you have a quality product, then the language does not matter.
Ukrainian will be as popular as Russian.
Where did you get this format?
I came up with it myself. I came up with everything myself.
I even remember where at the ASK I
came up with who should be the first guest.
The first guest was supposed to be named Made in Ukraine.
That is, everyone who became
popular during the Ukrainian era.
And who were they?
Well, El Kravchuk, if you remember him.
Yes.
Rusya Pysanka, Klichko brothers, who then lived in Kyiv.
They came to me, I thought I
showed them like this with my finger.
They came to me and said, we
will be the champions of the world.
First of all, they are white.
At the time when I made the program,
the champions of the world were only black.
And here are two such idiots, white.
They come and say, we will be the
champions of the world in professional boxing.
Well, you need to turn on your brains.
And here are a few such people.
Then I realized that we just didn't have so many stars.
Then came Blokhin, but Blokhin was
not Made in Ukraine, but Made in the USA.
Well, yes.
But the first five or seven, I don't even
remember how many programs there were.
I said, no, we only need those who were born in 1991.
And they gained popularity
not because of Moscow,
not because they were
shown on central television.
Well, it was such a concept.
Lyosha came up with the name Taboo.
Rodnyansky.
Yes, Rodnyansky.
Was there a political influence,
censorship, or reviews?
It was, it was.
Did Rodnyansky stand with a
shield in front of everyone?
No, no, it was difficult.
This is ambiguous.
Here Rodnyansky becomes such a double or triple or quadrilateral.
Because he needed it, this was his business.
This is his responsibility.
This is the money of Launder.
I don't know if it was necessary to give it away.
Was it business for him or still a political influence?
Business, business, business, of course.
No, he didn't want to give it away.
He then went on STS or something.
Right.
Well, in short, he started something in Russia.
Just the condition of his transition was
that the channel had no news.
And there are no political… He burned
himself, because, yes, it can be understood.
Yes, and he wanted to, he just tried to avoid it.
Although I could convince him, and
we had a huge scandal, as a result, I left.
Just because… Well,
how was it then?
It wasn't the same as it is now.
In principle, censorship exists in one way or another.
Well, in comparison with
the 1990s, it is not censorship at all.
But then there was total censorship.
For example, if you like Malevich,
and the friend of the owner of the
channel doesn't like Malevich, the artist,
and you came and said that the
exhibition of Malevich is wonderful,
then tomorrow you will
be expelled from work.
Because that person called
and said, What's up, Vasya?
This Malevich is s**t.
And this fool says that he is good.
What are you allowed to do there?
It was everywhere.
Sports.
Only the weather seemed to be untouched.
Although I don't know, I'm not sure.
And I remember, I was in charge…
When Tkachenko left, I was in charge of TSN for a couple of months.
Oh my God.
Well, I'm such a boss, we have such a daily order, etc.
And then Lazarenko was the prime minister.
Well?
What?
Why do allow Lazarenko to speak out?
What the hell is that?
Well, it's not Rodnyansky, I won't
say the name.
Or maybe I will one day.
And I thought, okay.
The next day, I say, let's do something.
Lazarenko, not in the first place, but in the second.
Hello, do we not have the prime minister of this country?
You didn't have a choice.
On the third day, you can say, let's not
put him in the third place, but in the eighth.
And on the fourth day, he's not there at all.
And on the fifth day, why is he not there?
Our prime minister is not there.
And on the fifth day…
You couldn't kick him?
You should have hit him in the face.
And on the tenth day…
Not so much.
A little bit.
Why are you hitting him in the face?
And you sit there, damn it.
There are no options.
I always… But there are
unique people among us.
Slava Pihovshchek always impressed me.
Obviously.
And I think there are such people in Moscow now.
Is he a phenomenon or not?
Why?
Because, you know, most
people have the impression that
censorship is when I, for
example, the presenter,
call the presidential administration
and say, what am I supposed to say here?
No, no, no.
I have to feel it.
Because these people are busy with business.
They need to steal from the state.
There are many things in the state that can be stolen.
And I have to know this
without taking consultations,
without calling, but feeling that
now we need to stress it right here.
Unique people.
I am delighted.
It didn't work out that way.
And did Pikhovshek understand this?
Yes.
He is unique precisely because
he understood how it goes up there.
How it goes there, where it goes there.
How can you understand if
you are not there?
No, well, he always said he
was there, but he had never been there.
Oh, I see.
He constantly talked about
it, emphasizing that he was
on a first-name basis, as they said
in the 19th century in the Russian
Empire,
on a first-name basis with the president.
And I was tired to listen to it.
I remember saying to someone,
I will not say name, ...
And when you go to the president, well, this is
all over the world, this is not only in Ukraine.
It's everywhere, in the US, anywhere.
They write it down.
You can't just come in without writing that you
have been there for so long, it's a security.
And I say to them, go to the
president's office, Kuchma,
and see when he has
been there for the last time.
He goes in and says...
It was in the summer of
some year, he says, in January.
I see a big combination.
Yes. But it's real art.
It's art to guess in the
distance what's going on in the big house.
Well, it's like that. He set 1+1
up, I must say.
And then…
1+1 apologized,
Aleksandr Yefimovich – in the same way?
This page, by the way… Yes,
but there wasn`t everything ambiguous.
Unambiguous?
Unambiguous, yes.
And just people at 1+1... I think
some part, not all, not everyone,
understood that the wind
won't blow in that direction.
Really, it's… You weren't there at all.
You were already on the 5th channel.
Yes, I was already on the 5th
channel. But I… Well, since
not much time has passed,
I know many people.
In fact, most of them have not changed in appearance.
I would not say that the behavior of 1+1
was as perfect as possible, not
only because of Pikhovshen, not only.
I think that Lyosha Rodiansky
was well-organized,
and he understood that if
we say that this is business,
then it is necessary to save it, and
there was already a feeling.
I did not have a feeling that
we had won on the 5th channel.
I was afraid that something would
happen to me until the last moment.
Well, until the third round.
Yes.
And people who, maybe because he
was in Moscow and was more away from it,
because I was watching it from the inside,
and he was on the side, maybe it
helped him to tell himself that it`s not right.
We are not going there.
Yes, we are losing something here.
We are coming in.
Yes. And so it was. And then it went on.
But, listen, these are all very difficult moments.
And until TV is not a business, until
there is no option of freedom, it cannot be.
All the talks about the fact
that TV can somehow speak the truth,
the American can, because this
is a business, these are profits.
Ethier in 2017 or 2018,
I don't remember, they added 800 million dollars.
It is also such a story, Mr. Mykolo.
Because, you know, if CNN is for democracy,
and Fox is for the Republicans,
then this is already a split, right?
But the problem is that this is their
belief, not an instruction.
They just don't hire Fox people
who will sympathize with the Democrats.
They don't hire in CNN...
Do we already copy this system?
Do we have channels?
Unfortunately, I don't know.
We don't have such a division.
Only in the worst possible way, I think.
The question is different. It is very simple.
Here is a billionaire sitting, and Natalka Moseichuk has a rating of 50%.
And Mykola Veresen has a rating of 5%.
And here he is, this billionaire, who
pays so much to maintain the channel.
In any way.
When there is Oprah Winfrey, who earned a billion for herself,
and how much she earned for the channel, it's just hard to imagine.
And that rich man, who is the owner.
Well, how is it? I won't take away Oprah.
Then I'll just throw money out of my pocket.
And in Ukraine, there is no such thing.
Either the worst presenter.
Or the best. Either a program with the
highest ratings.
Or a program with the lowest ratings.
I add up to 100 million per year.
Before the war, the 1+1 came to zero.
Well, it's not a profit, Natalka, it's not a profit.
When it's equal ... I agree, absolutely.
Then it will work.
All journalism is like this, this, and that.
Maybe now this TikTok is all modern.
Or some YouTube.
It's very difficult there.
Maybe something will change there. I don't know.
It will change if the business starts to work normally.
Because we are dependent on the business.
Even though we're going to burst, but
we
will not be able to have
a host become Oprah
and bring millions and billions to the channel.
No, not yet.
No, listen, we are secondary, we are tertiary.
The question is not that.
The question is that
television works
in those countries where there is
good production and good salaries.
When each Ukrainian has a salary of 500 dollars,
advertisers understand that we about 10%...
we collect this money, well, through advertising.
And we have 30 or 40 million.
We take 500 dollars for 40 million, multiply it, and then take 10%.
And we have billions on the market.
Well ... Then Natalka will get
a million a year, for example.
But we don't have such salaries.
Well, first, we don't have such
salaries, because the second is reality.
Because what will happen to television?
It is now only known to God.
And such a period is critical.
It will either go up and, supposedly,
become CNN or Fox after the war.
No, it will never become CNN.
Or ... Impossible, because ...
It will become such an entertainment
option of something, where there will be only ...
No, it will be like this.
You see, we have a colonial country.
For a long, long time.
When my young colleagues ask me,
why there is no BBC, what should we do?
I say, no, it won't work.
The British have an interesting world
because their neighbor was born in India.
And that's why the British are interested in the news about India.
About Burma, about this, about Africa.
Who cares about Burma in Ukraine?
That's it.
I would ask another question.
Are they ready to work like on the BBC?
Because of the way they work there on the BBC,
we would already be shouting, censorship,
restriction of my journalistic rights, and so on.
Because it is very, very ...
It is an obstructed system, I would say.
But, okay, we will not judge. They have their own rules.
Kuchma and Gongadze.
That's right ... That's
right, I won't say.
That's right, such
... I won't say.
A difficult story.
But you know, right?
No, I just know ... Why
don't you talk about it?
Den Borisovich Yanevsky
didn't talk about that.
He also said that he knows
who ... No, I guess ... How?
I know the vector, I don't know by name.
I know the vector, I am strongly of great doubt
that Kuchma was somehow involved there.
And I strongly ... In general, I
will say this phrase beautifully.
Cherchez la femme.
I won't say anything more.
You know, the whole country knows who you are targeting.
But no one wants to touch it because all the figures are alive.
More or less, yes.
It's incorrect in relation to both memory and…
No, it's not that. I stopped
this wave and this fashion for a long time.
I'll give you an example.
When Kryvenko Sashko crashed in the car,
they wanted to do the second
episode of Gongadze.
And they wanted to politicize it.
I was just burying Sashko in Lviv.
And I had to go back to Kyiv because
Taras Pratsuk died right that day in Baghdad.
In Iraq.
Yes. And these were my two closest friends.
And they just started
saying, let's raise this scandal,
come on, come on, come on,
we'll earn political dividends on this.
And I just called a lot of people.
I called Yulia, I said, Yulia,
I beg you, Tymoshenko, stop.
And she said, I heard
you, I understood your logic,
okay, that's it, we're not going to use it.
Just understand how people
really like to exploit politics today.
And still, journalists are not really politicians.
Well, they shouldn't be politicians at all.
During the war, probably should.
Well, you can't not be a patriot,
you can't be independent.
From the state.
Yes, from the society, from the state, you know.
We take the BBC example and do it right,
and we have to follow it.
But we also have to remember
that in the British territories, when
there was a war? There was never a war.
There were not a thousand years.
Here, Wilhelm, the winner, came.
This, this, this was a disaster.
And so only rockets flew from above.
Therefore, you can be independent there.
And they are really independent.
The BBC was against the
expansion of the Suez Canal,
against the Maldives, the
Falkland Islands, and so on.
But it's not here.
What would the BBC be like if there
was an invasion of the Kingdom of Kent?
Well, such, serious, with a foreign presence.
What would they say?
We don't know.
There just wasn't, there was no evidence,
there was no basis for evidence.
It's not exactly against the invasion of Falkland
but about Margaret Thatcher's politics.
Thatcher, yes, well, Thatcher always
liked to close the BBC, but nothing came of it.
But that's why we don't know how,
where the truth is, you know.
Today, there are no BBC standards in Ukraine.
Well, what is the war going on,
and what will you say?
So, you want to say that this whole story,
it all leads to such a human, difficult situation?
Well, I'd say that in 20 years,
when it will be described, it will
turn out to be very simple, just human.
You know, no one has invented anything more
intelligent than Shakespeare
in the last 400 years.
All the plots, they are described there.
But.
In the books.
Yes.
But anyway, you and I used
to go out and carry the banner
'Who killed Gongadze', and there was
also the banner 'Who ordered Gongadze.'
And ordering Gongadze is already a political story.
You see, when you build a country, it
seems to us, since the age of a person is short,
and we, me, who lived then,
obviously, at that time, we were all
politicized, very much, and I was politicized.
And we were looking, we were looking
for who is guilty, where is he, where is she.
And, as a rule, we looked somewhere up at the president.
Now I have become so
wise that I understand that
even today, when everything is politicized,
I still try to somehow
... Well, not...
...not to wear this outfit on myself.
And when now there is
criticism of those or others,
Zelensky, Zaluzhny,
and so on, I am so quiet.
I do not allow myself much,
because I understand that,
well, not in time, you know, not in time.
And this is also a
controversy, because today,
on the one hand, it is obvious that
it is difficult during the war to still,
as it were, direct the
bayonets to the government,
which is in fact bears responsibility for what is happening.
And, on the other hand, it is necessary to
understand something about freedom of speech.
And how to find a contact here between the
fact that there were no cases ... Well, yes.
I specially studied the British
press during the Second World War,
the American press during the Second
World War, and I watched what was there.
Well, there was censorship everywhere, everywhere there was ...
Somehow they were trying
to find a way to ...
And on the other hand, there was criticism,
and how to unite it today in today's Ukraine?
I do not know.
I have no answer.
Unfortunately, I do not belong to
those brilliant Ukrainian politicians,
historians, politicians
who know everything.
I do not know everything.
In the sense, we are going our own way as we are going it.
No, we ... And God knows
what will happen there.
As I told you, it is a natural historical process.
We cannot come up with anything.
We give birth to what we give birth to.
When we can give birth.
Neither sooner nor later.
Kuchma is accused of cutting back on airplanes.
Yushchenko cut off the last ones.
Even without Gongadze.
He is accused of the creation of a clan of the oligarchic system.
And so on.
Does it also apply?
Otherwise, we could not?
Without oligarchs, we could not?
We could have ... We
could have ... There could be another way.
But I do not know which way would be better.
I do not know which way would be better.
Unfortunately, there are no handbooks.
If there was a handbook where it was written
one the first page, chapter 1, 1991, do this, this, this, this, this.
I have not seen such a handbook.
And for some reason, the Estonians
and the Poles succeeded very quickly.
The Slovaks waited a very long time for them to succeed too.
The Romans and the Bulgarians are still half
... Well, they are in the European Union.
But to say that they are so ...
With corruption, everything is wonderful,
everything is subdued, you can not say.
Therefore, Ukraine went like this, Georgia went like this.
Belarus, you see, did not go like this at all.
Azerbaijan went like this in the Middle East.
No one knows how.
The Baltic is the same, you know.
And salaries in Estonia ...
In fact, in Estonia, the only ones who
caught up
with the Western Europeans in salaries.
Therefore ... Well, they could quickly ...
Could they pull us from the USSR faster?
No.
Our presidents?
I'm sure here.
No one will pull anyone.
In 2004, I was one of the people
who were in contact with various CRU people.
Well, before the Orange Revolution.
I then asked directly, I say,
what are we doing here? You
have a lot of money, let`s go.
And they said, until you have 100 thousand on
the Maidan, we will not lift a finger.
By ourselves, by ourselves.
Yes.
More than that. It was all explained.
They told me that we are in the
1960s and 1970s in Latin America.
This was the Monroe Doctrine of the 1820s.
This is our backyard.
And we decided that this is our backyard.
And then we, sorry for such phrase,
we f**ked up wherever
we could in Latin America.
And then we realized,
you start, and we can only...
My father told me about his father,
that is, my grandfather Mercury,
who said a wonderful phrase,
very simple, very beautiful, he said,
Kostya, you pick it up, and
I'll push it. Not vice versa.
So we have to pick it up, and they can
push it, but this is our job, our responsibility.
This is the kind of society we have today.
You have been to Crimea
a lot, and you once said
that you are ashamed of the Tatars,
and you always apologize to them.
Well, yes, it was in 1990
or 1991, I don't remember,
there was Grach, the head of
Crimea, and there was Kravchuk,
and we met in the Verkhovna Rada in Crimea.
I went up to him and said, listen,
let's give Crimea and Donbas them, and
we'll be in Europe the day after tomorrow.
I just said that without
thinking about the fact that,
by giving Crimea back, I
give the crowd of people
under the name of the Crimean Tatar
minority, who are our brothers.
So yes, I repeat, it's always,
it's not a secret, I'm really ashamed of it.
But today we see some traces
of what I said then, we see them today.
We see them, Donbas and Crimea.
Do you think that Crimea in the
historical context will still be a special territory?
Well, from the historical perspective, I think
that in 100 years Crimea will be Crimean Tatar.
Not Ukrainian.
There may be some combination, but
we don't know what will happen in 100 years.
But the fact that many people want
to have their statehood is obvious.
And the Crimean Tatar people don't have more land.
No, they don't.
So it will depend on what the mood will be then.
Do you understand?
That's all.
You ask Kravchuk, Kuchma.
The first person whom my eyes saw, who
said that the world has changed fundamentally,
and there is no turning in the
undemocratic direction, was Levko Lukyanenko,
who came out of prison a year
before he said that, from the tribune.
It was in 1990.
It was in May or April.
Our Frensis Fukuyama.
And he said that that's all.
And we asked him what was going on there.
It was a congress.
When the dissidents gathered,
the Ukrainian Helsinki Association
turned into the Ukrainian Republican Party.
It was in a Movie House.
And then he was the host.
I thought that I would climb under the table and die there.
Because they were just swearing.
The Soviet authorities did not cancel anything.
The Central Committee, the district committee,
the regional committee, the KGB, the police.
Everything is here.
People come out here and say that this will not happen.
This will not happen.
And I asked him why.
Because the world has changed.
And democracy has won.
And civilization has won.
And so we can be calmer.
We won`t be put in prison anymore.
Poor Levko Lukyanenko.
How he experienced 2004.
And then not the Orange Revolution.
And how... Excuse me.
He sat on that s**t.
Do you remember what happened?
Three rounds of elections.
How it was on the only channel that
was on the side of the Orange Revolution.
How with this one small TV channel
and a few unfortunate cameras
an alternative, opposition picture was made.
And yet they managed to... At first,
they were all in scarves on the stage.
They then managed to argue.
Well, that's how it should be.
It's all-natural.
Everything goes naturally.
No... Moreover... You
see, everyone was on time.
Even Yanukovych was on time.
Because if it hadn't been for Yanukovych,
I don't know what would have happened.
If he hadn't shown striptease, completely all.
And people...
Not people, but some people were shocked and
understood that something needed to be taken by force.
So... But democratic
values were promised.
Freedom was promised.
The deprivation of clanhood was promised.
The Orange Revolution.
They became the government and kept the same thing.
And then this clanhood... They
didn't keep anything, Natalka.
Ukrainian corruption, Ukrainian
clanhood are not in the Pechersk hills.
Where?
Because as long as we say that the fish rots from
the head, we will sit in the s**t where we sit.
Vasya Pupkin sits in the village.
His brother Petya Pupkin
wins the election to the village head.
Vasya Pupkin comes to Petya and says, listen, let me open
two shops, only don't give permission to open the third.
And then we will share everything
with you, and we will have it.
From bottom to top,
all these conversations,
that somewhere the minister, or the president, or the
prime minister, or whoever steals something there.
I want there to be no corruption, but I
want to be able to make an agreement quickly.
And this is how we live.
And maybe 10-20% of people don't give bribes.
If you come in, there are a lot
of people sitting and drinking beer.
Saturday.
In Tallinn.
We drink beer.
Veresen is getting late.
Half an hour after everyone has already
sat down he comes and apologizes and says,
listen, guys, I'm sorry, I was just stopped by
the police, I made a long deal, gave a bribe.
Everyone says, well done, great.
If I say that in Tallinn, no one will talk to me tomorrow.
If I say that in Warsaw, no one will talk to me tomorrow.
I'm not talking about London.
And in Ukraine, well done, good boy.
And this is how 90% do it.
Okay, 80%.
After 2014, maybe after this war, it will be 75%.
But a huge majority, if they
criticize the government tomorrow,
it's because they have no power.
Critics of the government.
When I look at some people, I won't call
their names,
I look at how they describe the bad.
They, damn it, sit in the Four Seasons hotel
and drive, damn it, on a Mercedes 600.
And I see the saliva flowing from him.
F**k, I want to be in his place.
Four Seasons, I want, I want a Mercedes 600.
There is.
Yes.
And they are very, very, very,
it is clear to them that this is jealousy.
And tomorrow that chief critic will say, damn it.
Why?
This is how it can be.
I already a deputy minister there.
I know.
And this is not about nationalists.
I knew, but I will not remind.
In 2004, how is it, these
energy resources were headed by
the head of CUN, the Congress
of Ukrainian Nationalists.
And what?
And the same.
Not Slava Stetsko, no.
And not her husband.
But maybe Slava Stetsko would have said, no, no, no.
Let's be somehow different.
So I am very careful with people who are the biggest critics.
They don`t like everything.
They just didn't give them pay.
If they had given them pay, maybe they would have liked it more.
There are some events when you worked on Channel
5 and we did the Orange Revolution together.
Are you ashamed of your actions?
I am ashamed every day.
Every day.
Orange Revolution.
Tell me about the revolution.
In fact, we were very envious of the people who came.
It's demobilized.
We work on Channel 5.
Den Borisovich, Mr. Mykola, demobilized come.
They have polished plaques.
With our hands.
And what?
Yes.
They come and tell them about responsibility.
I was triggered.
Veresen is responsible.
And I am always responsible.
I tell.
It's 12 o'clock.
I make a change.
Verosen calls and says, I'm responsible.
I can't come to the broadcast.
And Moseychuk plays this broadcast until the night, until 12 o'clock.
And I remember that day very well.
But I brought out another fable.
That you deserved it.
Well, maybe.
And even you can afford it.
Because you have done a lot before that.
And you deserved it.
It doesn't mean that you need to establish a grandfatherhood.
No.
I just don't want to...
But I was humorous when Mykola came.
Mykola has an assistant.
Angela, yes.
She was sitting at the keyboard.
Mykola said, write.
My name is Mykola Veresen.
And then write yourself.
No, it's not true.
Well, it's true.
What am I going to lie about?
Let's call Angela right now.
She will confirm or simplify.
No.
I know that I never
... I always don't ...
It's very difficult for me to read someone else's texts.
It just doesn't work for me.
I can't read someone else's texts.
That's why I always write everything myself.
And someone else can print it.
That's another matter.
But I always ... She printed it.
But I always ... I never ... I just have
something ... I have physiological problems.
I can't pronounce someone else's texts.
I've never done that.
And moreover, I know for sure.
I won't say the name.
But I know for sure that after the
earlier broadcast, I changed all the texts.
And after me, no one changed.
No one changed.
No one changed the texts.
They read my texts.
There was a requirement to change 90% of the upgrade.
Roman Skrypin set such a requirement then.
And Andrii Shevchenko.
No.
Well, listen.
This is really not deserved.
I'll tell you one thing.
When I came in 1990, it was the British days in Kyiv.
Basically, the BBC came to Kyiv then.
And then I started to work tet-a-tet.
Not through the phone.
I asked then.
I say, in principle, you can calculate.
I already understood the kitchen.
That I ... Not that I
will say my opinion.
Well, I'll hint.
They say, well, yes.
I say, and when?
Well, 8-10 years.
I still don't understand this word.
Now, when I say it like that,
as you say, as many people say.
And others, on the contrary, say this version is s**t.
It is unknown who is right.
When you are at home.
You can hint when you are so famous in the family.
Which turns on the TV, computers, etc.
I ... Well, I know him.
I have known him not for a year, and not two, and not three.
And he is at home with me.
He is a family member.
He is here somewhere with me.
Then there are such moments.
And when you are 25 years old, 35 years old.
You came yesterday and you say.
You need to take off this skirt,
but you have to wear green here.
Who is he?
When I have one program about fashion every day.
And everyone knows that I have such a good taste.
And I say, here you need green.
And here you need red.
And here you need yellow.
And here you need
... Everyone says.
Well, he is, in
principle ... Trust.
Yes.
In 10 cases, 8 he guessed.
Okay.
We will both believe.
And if you came suddenly.
You have been talking about cycling sports for a long time.
And then you came and said.
Your skirt is not green.
You need here...
Are you talking about bicycles?
Or about the skirt?
Or about politics?
Or about economics?
Well, there was such dissatisfaction.
That is what we led them to.
I don't know.
Did you know that they did not have
consolidation in the orange team inside?
Or did they all argue together along the way?
Did you have dissatisfaction after the Universals?
After Timoshenko with Yanukovych?
No, no, no.
I had.
I did not have the same dissatisfaction.
I was worried.
But again, age.
Such an infection.
This is age.
You know, I remember in 1992, when
Viktor Penzenyk did not resign somewhere.
For the administration of Kuchma.
Kuchma was the prime minister.
And something there.
And I was so angry.
Now I am ashamed.
For being angry then.
And then I complained to him.
Because then it was...
Once we sat with Martinenko Sasha.
A beautiful phrase was born.
About Balserovysh?
Yes.
You know, right?
If Penzenyk lived in Poland.
He would have been Balserovysh.
If Balserovysh had lived in Ukraine.
He would have been Penzenyk.
There are no options.
Just because.
Well, the country was ready.
You say.
It was possible there.
It is possible.
I said then, by the way.
I said it then, too.
If in 1991.
Then 52 million Ukrainians.
All as one.
Or at least two-thirds. Although three quarters is better.
They agreed as it was in
Estonia, in Poland, in Georgia,
without electricity, without water,
without heat, to live for 2-3 years.
Maybe then we could
have kept nuclear weapons.
It was a very simple story. I saw
it all. I was at these negotiations.
The Americans are sitting
and saying, give us weapons.
I'm vulgarizing, simplifying
as much as possible.
Here I have a billion, you have zero.
You have just zero. Here I have a
billion, and here I have an open hand.
Put a bomb here for
me. All of you. Come on.
Find me a politician who says, I'm not going to tell the
nation, the people, but I'm going to convince the people.
Let's clench our teeth and we'll
be hungry for 3 years. Without electricity.
Well, it happened. Without electricity, but without you. Without heat.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no. With electricity,
with heat, everything worked. Everything.
I say it caught up with us.
When Zelensky comes out now and
says, we need electricity but without you.
Without heat, but without you, Russians.
Well, listen, it caught up. It's the 24th.
I was sitting on the 24th of August 1991
in the halls of the Verkhovna
Rada, up there, and next to me
was Kulik, the future
Minister of Information, Zinoviy.
Vitaliy Kulik.
No, Zinoviy.
Zinoviy Kulik.
We were sitting there by accident.
And so they vote,
there are 361 or 362, and the
decision is made. Kravchuk, everything...
So, there will be blood.
And this was not my emotion.
It is jus that, as a historian, I am a terrible
historian. I cannot say that I am a great historian.
But I just saw some patterns there a little, read something sometimes.
And he says … why?
I say because, well, freedom is not given free.
Now, after 2004, I said this phrase that
the currency paid for freedom is called blood.
Freedom does not accept other currencies.
This is the only currency.
And when you were given it for free in 1991,
then they started to remind me, no,
and 100 years ago, and Bandera, and this.
I say, no, no, you have to be here and now.
You have to start the process today
and constantly lead it, maybe for
decades, but starting from today.
And then it is counted.
If you started 100 years ago and
lost 90 years, it is not counted.
So we started in 1991.
Then we continued in 2004.
Then we continued in 2014.
Now in 2022.
And when we get the case to
the end, then we will have freedom.
As wise people say, the case is not
over until it is not over correctly.
It is not over?
Ours is not over yet.
And the right thing is Ukraine.
In the European Union, in NATO.
Fully.
That is, even if now Ukraine enters with parts as some propose.
Are you now?
I do not mind.
By the way, I do not see any nightmare here.
I am GDR, FRG.
Nothing.
A wonderful story.
You have to at least put your foot in there.
In the door, you know, so that they do not close.
Well, I want everything immediately.
We are Ukrainians, after all.
Ukrainians, everything is immediate.
We do not need these parts.
Therefore, it will be interesting.
I do not exclude any options.
You know, I do not exclude.
I understand that there may be good
options, average options, and bad options.
And if the bad option is what will happen to the people?
As you say.
If we have to forget about the borders of 1991.
Why forget?
Well, the Baltics too.
Listen, we have a wonderful example called Finland.
In the 1940s, it had completely different borders.
Russia, or rather the Soviet Union, took the territories and still lives there.
But they kept themselves.
They kept Finland, the Finnish language,
Finnish culture, Finnish economy.
They kept themselves.
Ukraine, I said it in March 2022.
If there are three regions left, then Putin has lost.
Because his goal is not to have any
region, but for everything to be Russia.
That's all.
But if you ... How to say?
Do you understand?
Now the artificial intelligence
was sent to...
How to solve these crises, crisis problems.
And the whole artificial intelligence says, let's throw a bomb.
We have it, but if we have a bomb, why don't we use it?
Let's throw it.
The military always operates on the worst scenarios.
Just the worst.
And I also operate on the best, the worst, and the average.
I have my friends there, foreigners.
They say, well, listen, it can't be forever.
I say that is, here is a Canadian, a Brit, a German.
The war is going on.
They supply arms in one way or another.
Ammunition, money there, everything.
The war is going on for a year, two, three, five.
How long does it take for it to go?
Without the victory of Ukraine and without the victory of Russia.
And? How many?
And sooner or later, a German,
an Austrian, a Canadian, an American.
They`ll sit - let's end it. Under any circumstances.
With Crimea, without Crimea, so and so.
Are we excluding it 100%?
I wouldn't say so.
That's why I think we have all the options on the table for now.
Of course, Ukrainians want to have a good option.
What can you say to the people?
We need to talk for a long time.
Especially those who...
This is a matter of fine matter.
Because we can talk like some politicians.
And we can talk shorter.
The question is always the language.
If we have a question, who will talk to the people?
It's like mobilization.
We have an elected president.
We have a government.
And they have to gradually and gradually
say that there is such and such an option.
Now Zelensky's position, as I understand it, I don't know.
I didn't hold a candle.
We need optimism and patriotism.
And I'm not saying it's bad or good.
I don't comment on it.
Because he's the president.
I'm not the president.
That's what he thinks.
Okay, maybe he has more information.
No.
He definitely has more information than I do.
Let him see it that way.
Now the question is, if Trump wins,
will anything change or nothing?
If they give these 60 billion or not,
will we withstand the pressure on the front or not?
Can we mobilize, well, okay, not
500,000, but 400,000, okay, 300,000?
Or can we not?
That's just a question.
Do you think that the conversation with the country,
if the government comes out and says
that we do not withstand the pressure
and we will stop in deep defense, will
it end with the consolidation of society
and the preservation of that part of
Ukraine that was liberated from the Russians?
Difficult. The conversation will not be easy.
Will the country survive after this conversation?
Listen, our problem, the problem of Ukrainians is that,
and, by the way, journalists, and you, and
me, it is that we, looking at social networks,
see there are 3-5, a maximum of 7 percent,
but so active, who are constantly shouting,
everything is gone, they take
off their clothes, the client leaves.
Do you think it's 3-5 percent of them?
I don't think so, I'm talking to sociologists.
I'm talking to sociologists on purpose.
People are much wiser, they just keep silent.
Those who are wiser, who are 80 percent, they keep silent.
And those who speak from morning to
night, that everyone around is guilty,
there are 3-5, a maximum of 7 of them.
But there are so many of them,
they are so bright, they shout so loudly.
Natalka, it's all right, Ukrainians are not such idiots.
Although there are, they happen, there are, there are.
That is, you don't have such a feeling of
a deep split in Ukrainian society?
There is nothing close, there is nothing close.
And in Lviv, where you live, there is no such thing either?
Listen, there are different people everywhere.
That is, here I am, we began to donate less.
I'm talking to the banks.
Well, Gorokhovsky came out and said more, yes.
In one and a half times, the 2023 year gave more than the 2022.
What kind of nonsense is this?
Someone, to someone, one woman,
the woman said, as they say about the BBC.
Here I read, everyone stopped speaking
the Ukrainian language, back to Russian.
We didn`t all speak totally Ukrainian,
in the 2022 year we suddenly had such a magical tummler.
And 100% speaks Ukrainian.
No, they will speak Russian for a long time.
There are places where they will speak.
And you will not go anywhere.
You will not do anything with it.
Nature is like that.
This is how we lived.
So I don`t see any splits.
Yes, I think I can greet the Kremlin.
Because this is gradual.
Here it is bad, here it is bad.
Everyone shouted.
They take off their clothes and leave.
And that's it.
You know, it's probably the age.
I have long said that everyone who is on the stage,
they all need them, Ukraine needs them.
The nation itself will choose.
These are elections.
We can't do anything about it.
When they started..., I read today that
some idiots, I will not say their names,
they were very serious idiots.
Usurpation of power.
I say, listen, the people came and said,
this guy has 73%, these guys have 50%.
23% and 70%.
No, no, no.
I'm not talking about the parliament.
There are 50% and something.
Well, let's cancel it all.
Well, that's what happened.
People voted like that.
This is bad.
Well, bad.
I don't know.
But these are people, not me.
I, for example, didn't vote for it.
But I, well, if it's a democracy, do I have to
agree with the majority or what should I do?
How should I behave?
Raise the revolution every five years.
Because I don't like this president.
I don't like this council.
I don't like this prime minister.
I don't like these people at all.
Churchill told us that it was very bad.
Democracy is very, very, very imperfect.
It's better to come up with something.
Let's do it like in Moscow.
Everything is fine there.
The man came and said, here you
will be like this, walk as I said.
And that's it.
And by the way, a lot of people, these
7%, about whom I said, this is their dream.
I'm just saying,
what are they for?
They are for democracy.
No, no, no.
They want everyone to be like them.
They want everyone to be.
They don't just write, I think.
People need.
Yes.
They always have a people.
People.
Savonarola was like that in Florence.
Everyone remembers great artists, sculptors,
but there was Savonarola, who was like that.
He had a lot of young
guys, very young.
And they just destroyed,
attacked, killed.
It would be good to destroy, to
attack, to kill, but not during the war.
And so, when I asked
you, do you feel the split?
I'm very triggered.
I won't hide it.
And I'm always worried about such movements.
And especially this
one, the last discourse.
I don't know.
Of course, when we go
on air, I think it will end.
But nevertheless, I think it's quite
dangerous when politicians separate people
along the lines of Zaluzhny and Zelensky.
Just a second.
It will happen.
What luck for the Russians.
It happens.
People remain people.
You can't go anywhere.
There will be scandals.
People have gathered during the beginning
of the war, as always, in a new affair.
This is not even a military affair.
You asked about 1+1.
When 1+1 appeared,
everyone was burning brightly.
No one wanted to make a mistake.
Everyone was next to each other.
Everyone was holding on to each other.
Come on, we will now prove that
Ukrainians can do great television.
Let's find such and such.
Let's find this type.
All together.
A year passes.
Two passes.
That's it.
It ends.
By the way, I don't know.
I don't have either. I don't have my point of view. I see a lot...
In general,
I would say that this Zelensky-Zaluzhny is
such, in fact, it is a very simple story.
This is a story about the fact that
two people have about 95% in common.
But through our colleagues, through me, through
you, through everyone, through many, many,
and those who write on the Internet, we,
these 5%, became so important that they are
more important than 95%.
Imagine that someone wants to lose,
does not want money
from America, someone does not want weapons
from America, someone
does not want Putin to die.
If you take and calculate how much they
have in common, then in common they are
like this.
And differently,
they are like this.
And they shout about it.
And so according to all
parameters, you just need to be calm.
Here I am, as it is called, when there
are commissariats, now there are some
three letters.
TCK.
I think on purpose, I am so smart
that I always dig into everything.
Scandals on the
fingers of one hand.
Something in Odesa,
something in Zakarpattia.
Well, such a thing.
And how many TCKs?
Hundreds.
It is less than a percent.
And the scandal is such that it is so
impressive that all TCKs are just fighting
on the heads of poor people on the street
and them in this immediate jail
and after jail
on the front.
Then somewhere I read Oh, 20,000
people were
detained on the border.
20,000!
There is a million in the front.
20,000 is two f**king percent.
That's much less than
in any army in the world.
Because those who want to go
through the war are much more.
Someone calculated how many
people were going freely to the front.
I talked with people from the front line.
They say we have queues.
But we don`t know about that.
We know that there is Vasya Pupkin who
said that he doesn't want to join the army.
And all newspapers, radio, TV, the
Internet wrote about Vasya Pupkin.
And the fact that there are 150 other people
who say that they are going to the front.
No, we don't know about it.
And this is everywhere.
Because we know about the louder ones.
And we know how those who shout
the loudest can take advantage of technology.
And to come to power on a grader
and then do what happened before him.
Well, people
don't really change.
I said at the beginning that
they change and don't change.
We can't find any...
It's just that these people
convince the country that it will be different.
Listen, if they won't convert,
then let's surrender to the Russians,
because no one is convincing anyone there.
If they convince the country...
They will not be convinced.
There aren`t so many of them.
But this is a big challenge.
On the one hand, you can't
support it because there is a war.
On the other hand, you can't close the mouse to
everyone, because why we`re fighting then?
Because in Russia
everyone's mouse is closed.
Then let's give up right away
and everything will be fine.
They're closed, we're
closed. There is no difference.
So you have to criticize.
So you think we can win with our mouths open?
Well, listen, democracy
always wins at a long distance.
So, you need to take your own hands
and understand that it won't end tomorrow.
Otherwise, it will
be bad for everyone.
You can't escape from this. It`ll be bad for everyone.
Should the government now say what kind of
country we are building? Right now, during the war.
There are such desires, but no one knows what to build the country.
Nobody knows.
There are such images of Europe.
Although Europe, you know, Sweden is Europe,
Portugal is Europe, Greece is Europe, Austria is Europe.
The origins of the foreign media say that Washington
asks Kyiv what would you do at the front line?
What kind of country are you going to build?
No, no, these are two different issues.
I have already painted
a picture at the front.
The story at the front is complicated
because there are no obvious things.
If the front will stand for a long time,
sooner or later they will say let's find a way to make peace.
Does this mean that
the conditional Zelensky
will be replaced by some party of
peace or the Minsk agreements?
Or Zelensky will mimic.
Thanks.
Or Zelensky, who is quite an elastic person, I think.
I think he can.
Now he may not have such thoughts.
Although I think there are.
I even sometimes think that this whole story
with Zaluzhny is not because it's between them,
but that we need to come up with a new vector.
Have you read the leaks from
the foreign press, where they say that...?
I just got a call from
a friend from Toronto
who is going to make a
movie and we had a long talk
about what the mood of Americans,
Europeans can be and so on.
And it's such a ...
We talked with him.
The only drawback of our conversation...this
is my old friend from CBC,
is that we counted only Ukrainians,
we haven`t counted Russians.
And we should count both Ukrainians and Russians.
Therefore, failures can befall both us and the Russians.
In the long, it will be much worse for Russians.
But then again, it's hard for me to imagine...
I've been saying since 1989 that I'm a democrat...
For me, democracy is important and I
understand that it is a value that we must fight for.
If there is no democracy, if
there is no criticism, if there is no
freedom of speech and freedom of
the press, then what are we fighting for?
I think we are fighting for freedom,
freedom of speech, freedom of the press.
And on the other hand, there is also a
contradiction in that
I don't like a lot of what I hear.
But this does not mean that I believe
that people, as you say, have been split.
That it is a 50-50 split.
It's 1 in 10.
And so I am more or less calm.
But what should we do? Ban freedom of speech? No.
Well, I'm just afraid of 1919,
100 years ago, you know,
but I would never have thought, Mr. Mykola,
that you could say this phrase that
Kravchuk did and Zelensky is doing one fundamental thing.
Kravchuk was pulling the
Ukrainian Republic out of the USSR,
and Zelensky is pulling Ukraine out of the
Ukrainian republic that was created after 1991.
One more point from Kravchuk...,
it's too early to talk about Zelensky,
it will take some time for
us to understand the history.
But what we forget is the peaceful
change of power from Kravchuk to Kuchma.
Zelensky did the same thing. He succeeded, despite the...
At first, these are all the consequences
of that sunny summer day, I remember it,
where we stood and I remember
now with Oleksandr Martynenko
in the Mariinsky Palace
and saw how it was changing.
We didn't pay that much attention to it at the time.
And now I realize that
the transition of power was laid down to
be difficult, but not like in Central Asia.
It was laid down, but it failed twice.
During the Orange Revolution and in 2014.
It failed, but the case was completed
anyway because it was completed correctly.
It's just always, as they say,
offensive, and especially in 2013-2014
because people are dead, you know?
And then history rolled back all the demands of the revolution.
Listen, we talked about paying for
freedom with blood. Nothing can be done.
Other currencies are not accepted.
This cash desk does not accept other currencies.
In a cash register called freedom... So everything is organic.
It hurts because it was in
front of our eyes, you know?
And if we look at the Polish
events, the partition of Poland, 1792...
everyone went through this.
Just because it's in front of our eyes,
and because there was a bombing last night,
and someone died, and terrible things are
happening, so yes,
we are living in such a period.
I didn't expect to see you like this, to be honest.
What am I supposed to be like?
No, I remember Mykola Veresen as quite emotional...
You know, I'm changing too,
and I generally think that people
who don't change are called idiots.
I think I would have come to the
Maidan if I had seen such a nightmare,
but I didn't see a nightmare.
I actually think we chose all this back in 2022 in March.
So my version is that as long as
the Ukrainian leadership doesn't call
Moscow, as long as this country is alive.
Moreover, tomorrow or the
day after tomorrow I will be
talking about this with
friends, various intellectuals.
It turns out that the institutions are very strong.
They're not perfect,
they're not perfect, but listen,
I didn't believe that we would
survive. I didn't believe it.
Question.
We have people who listened carefully, our viewers.
Right?
We have a format where the audience asks questions
Let them ask.
Good evening. My name is Alexander.
Please tell us if you have any of your
previous projects from the 90s and 00s
that you would like to return to
and how you would modernize them.
No, I don't have any, I'm
thinking about new projects.
If I had the money, if a billion fell from
the sky, I would make a fantastic channel.
But I understand that a billion won't fall
and I'm not going to update
anything because I've already done it,
I'm not interested, I
already know how to do it.
But what is new, I don't know,
maybe I could come up with something,
but today I don't think about it,
I think that there is a war now,
and God willing, we will stay where we are.
I go to work and tell people what is happening
at the front, in the rear, here and there.
I think it's a great
mission, and I'm doing it.
And now I think, oh,
what would have happened
if there was no war, if
I had a billion, if, if, if...
If my grandmother had a mustache and
a beard, she would be a grandfather.
Thank you.
Good evening, Mr. Mykola, my name
is Roman. You mentioned democratic values.
Actually, this is what distinguishes us
from Russians, what we are fighting for.
And I want to ask you about
freedom of speech during the war.
What should it be like? Who
should determine its limits, if any?
And where should we stop?
That is, can we, as media, as mass media,
inform society, for example,
about our losses, what they really are?
There is no answer to your question,
it does not exist in nature. There
is no answer to this question.
I have this rather provocative idea...
I was just asked this question
when the greatest chief of the
BBC came to Kyiv many years ago.
We were sitting in a restaurant
and this is always asked.
On June 3, 1944, you are a journalist
and you find out that there will be an
Anglo-American, Canadian landing in Normandy.
And you are a journalist,
you cannot hide information
and you have to write about it.
Today, on the 3rd, you wrote about
it, tomorrow Hitler will find out about it,
and the day after tomorrow
all these people will die.
What are your actions?
There's a nice positive story,
you'll laugh because it's absurd,
but it's the only thing
the BBC came up with.
That I write
and describe information beautifully, and
you, the editor, do not put it on the air.
I did my job as a journalist,
and you did yours as an editor.
It goes without saying
that this is not a solution.
But it is also clear that humanity
does not have an answer.
There are questions to which humanity has no answer.
When and where should be the limit
of freedom of speech?
By groping, like this.
Self-regulation at the editorial level?
There can be no self-regulation.
There are journalists
in Ukraine, but there is no journalism.
Because this is the main question.
You know, the principles of the workshop
are what civil society is all about.
If we don't tell doctors
that they are treating badly,
the doctors will say among themselves that
it's not our.
He violates ethics, so we decide.
Lawyers say it's not ours,
engineers say it's not ours, journalists say, no,
no, it's not a journalist, it's something else.
And then civil society emerges,
a society consisting of different communities.
Well, in addition to citizens,
there are also communities.
Philatelists say that he collects fake
stamps, he collects the wrong ones. And so on.
Without self-regulation,
nothing will happen,
and we cannot have self-regulation.
I did this in the 90s, as it is called...
we created a commission
on journalistic ethics
with the late Mostovyi. And with
Krivenko how many times we... this Ukraine.
Western colleagues gave us money
to explain journalism to judges.
To explain to journalists
how and where the trial.
With prosecutors, with
governors, oh my God.
There's nothing. At the moment
when self-organization begins,
when journalists suddenly say among
themselves, this is not a journalist.
It's not the Minister decision
and not a policeman's, but we
decided somewhere gathered and said
that this is not a journalist. At
that moment everything began.
Just as doctors say this is a bad doctor,
we do not take him to our workshop,
he does not know how to treat
people. And so on and so forth.
It turns out that for more than
30 years of independence
in Ukraine journalistic
workshop has not formed.
I think you know the
answer to that question.
It is obvious, but I would
give another example here.
In 1776, America became
a supposedly free country,
then they adopted a
constitution where that says,
all people are born free and
have the right to fight for happiness.
About 100 years passed when they
said that blacks were also people.
And then another 120 years passed
and a black president was elected
Therefore, it takes about 200 years for
something to change. And 30 is just nothing.
Good evening, my name
is Anna and I am a student.
I heard what you said, the Russian language, it
will be, and as if there is no point in fighting it.
Although I study journalism and think that
many young people would disagree with you.
This must be fought and
where do you get such
despondency, or are you just a realist?
Listen, I don't mind, fight.
Did I tell you not to fight you? Fight.
You know, there was one
such American president
who quoted another Ukrainian
writer 'Fight and you`ll succeed'.
If you know how.
Yes, so there are no questions,
and only students
would disagree and that's fine, I'm happy.
I remember in 1990 the first senators came to Kyiv.
I do not remember, it was nuclear weapons, Lugar there.
They came and we talked
about something there.
Well, I'm as sharp as a setro, I say
it badly, it's bad, it's bad.
And then the general speeches.
The senator says how cool it
is now in the former Soviet Union,
in the Ukrainian SSR, although we know that
it wants to become Ukraine without the USSR.
How cool that there is freedom of speech.
It was hard for me to imagine that a young,...
I was young then, I was not always like now, ...
a journalist and began to criticize.
It is impossible to imagine two years ago
someone will start
criticizing. So congratulations.
And I'm like, here you are...
Well, I just complain to him,
and he says, oh, that's freedom.
So you know, you fight.
I just know that you cannot eradicate what
has been imposed for
centuries, not years, not decades.
Not if you know where the secret
toggle switch is.
I always look for it, where there is this magic
toggle switch where it is written on and off.
And secondly, this is quite relevant now.
I just look, there is
such a Lviv lady Farion.
And here is such a delicate moment
what you want.
If you want to have a lot of
Ukrainian and little Russian
or extreme that there
was no Russian at all,
then you will not achieve the goal if
you say
Hey you, assholes, why do you speak in Russian?
It definitely won't come.
But if you say,
I understand these people, I understand
the age of prohibitions. I understand it.
I propose, let's create
teachers on the front
who will go if anyone
wants any consultations.
We will help, we understand
you, we want to help.
Then maybe such people will be
found and there will be more results.
And when you say, hey you assholes...
You know what I like,
thank God I'm not on social networks,
but when I read the news, I read reviews.
Well, 90% of the reviews in
some media - Yermak is terrible.
I say, if we imagine the need to defeat
Russia, then it seems to me that it comes first.
They write there, he must
be shot immediately.
I say maybe let's offer
him... If I am convinced
that after Yermak is gone and
there will be a Ukrainian flag over the
Kremlin,
I will be the first to go to the Maidan.
Moreover, I had a suspicion
that Yermak himself would say
that I would shoot myself in front of you
for the victory of Ukraine.
I am ready to shoot myself right on
Independence Square, you will see my  corpse.
But what will we do if our flag does
not loom over the Kremlin in this case?
In extreme cases, we apologize.
Yeah, yeah.
So I always say, if you want to
know the language - be friendly.
You will not learn the
language with swear words
and questions about why they
do not speak Russian.
After such words, it is unlikely that anyone
will want to learn the Ukrainian language.
And if you gradually learn...
As Sadovyi said, but with good.
Once we interviewed him.
With love, he said, but with love.
Look, no, not yelling, not shouting.
But you just said that, like, no, it will be Russian.
And you can't do anything about it,
you have to come to terms with it.
So I'm not ready to come to terms with it.
That is, you still need to do some actions.
For example, let's be specific.
Some are not suitable here.
Let's be specific.
One, two, three, four, twelve.
Well, to start what they are doing now, to target people.
And this is very abstract. What is targetting? How?
How to target?
Through content.
Through what?
What is content?
Even on YouTube.
Let's speak a language that everyone understands.
What is content and what is targetting?
It's the same as spirituality.
I love people very much who say, we need spirituality.
Let me touch the spirituality.
Let me, I want to watch.
Let me have content and target.
No, well, content is a filling.
Your division.
That's right.
On TV.
Now content.
Already on TV.
What's next?
What else?
YouTube.
There is no Russian language.
Next what?
How are we going to target?
No, no.
You know.
No, I don't know.
There are many, even Ukrainian bloggers.
Very famous.
Influencers.
Yes.
There are still those who speak Russian.
And they say, like, it's generally cool.
It's normal.
Yes.
Here I am against such.
I am also against it.
I have a proposition for you.
Only I will personally give you a gun.
So that you kill them.
Only with your own hands, please.
Not abstract to target.
And just take aim.
And press.
Listen.
Well, this is from the 90s.
Discussion, ideas, ideas.
It means that you, Anya, should become so bright
that your brightness will push those bloggers
who you are not satisfied with, out of this blogosphere.
You have to overcome them. People have to follow you.
Then what you say will become a reality.
There is another way, as Mr. Mykola says. These are years.
And the number of such people will be less and less.
Our identity will become more and more.
And if the world changes
and this world redesigning will
take place, it will possibly happen.
We don't know that.
We are modern people.
Perhaps the set of languages will be narrowed altogether.
It will be Spanish, English, and Chinese, for example.
Depending on how this ball changes.
We don't know anything. Because we have one idiot who
can launch a nuclear weapon at any time, you know,
and wash away one-sixth of the world,
which also speaks some language. No one knows.
More specifics, dear lady. This is not
a discussion. Aiming at content is nothing.
For the first time,
the Palace of Ukraine. Well, because
only today is Independence Day,
there was still such a
movement, well, as it were.
And there is in the basement,
well, under everything there,
they covered the tables, and
there would be some kind of cafe.
Not the cafe that we
all go to, but there it is.
And there is something like that.
And we are sitting with Naboka.
Naboka served in prison, as a dissident.
And we are sitting. And Naboka
had such an idea that let's drink champagne.
He decided that we needed to stop drinking, so let's have champagne.
Well, okay. And we drink champagne.
And so, I wouldn't say that we
drank a lot, really, there was one glass.
And Naboka is like this. Do you
know what I want to tell you?
That the people are fools.
And here, next to them, there
are such women, such Rukhivs,
such in handkerchiefs,
such real Ukrainians.
And they are like this, Mr. Sergei,
how can you say that?
You were in prison for the people.
You suffered for the people.
Mr. Sergei is sitting like this.
That's why I was in prison and
suffering, that the people are fools.
I would be sentenced for this,
and I would be shot here.
And Naboka, you know, five years
in prison
for nationalism, somehow he was like this.
And they just silently left.
And if I had been sitting, they
would have already buried me there.
Thank you very much.